<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://andygreenphd.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://andygreenphd.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-31T05:10:38+00:00</updated><id>https://andygreenphd.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andrew William Green, Ph.D.</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Is Georgia moving to hand-marked paper ballots for elections?</title><link href="https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2025/is-georgia-moving-to-hand-marked-paper-ballots-for-elections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Georgia moving to hand-marked paper ballots for elections?"/><published>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2025/is-georgia-moving-to-hand-marked-paper-ballots-for-elections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2025/is-georgia-moving-to-hand-marked-paper-ballots-for-elections/"><![CDATA[<p>The Georgia Assembly is considering a bill to return the state to hand-marked paper ballots as the default, with touchscreen voting devices available for people with disabilities.</p> <p>The bill won’t make it through the 2025 legislative session as it was not passed by the Senate before crossover day. Hopefully, it will survive the session and be ready for next year.</p> <p>I believe this is a very good move for the state, and I hope it passes next year and is signed into law by the governor. A 2018 National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine study recommended the use of hand-marked paper ballots for voting, as did Dr. Wenke Lee, the sole security member of a 2019 Georgia panel created to examine election security.</p> <p>hand-marked paper ballots are the safest and most secure way to ensure that a voter’s intent is counted as intended and provide a clean method for post-election audits (hopefully using the risk-limiting audit method).</p> <p>AJC reporting – <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/georgia-lawmakers-propose-switch-to-hand-marked-paper-ballots/WFF4W34YCJEBPNMIEPODCMFGWM/?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTAAAR0nLbIt23T8h2y7zTCy_-SOTLIZABxbMmsspc3LJRRwz20Z8OZiEux1x5M_aem_3bzzfM47-eKz8LI78tmUeg">https://www.ajc.com/politics/georgia-lawmakers-propose-switch-to-hand-marked-paper-ballots/WFF4W34YCJEBPNMIEPODCMFGWM/?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTAAAR0nLbIt23T8h2y7zTCy_-SOTLIZABxbMmsspc3LJRRwz20Z8OZiEux1x5M_aem_3bzzfM47-eKz8LI78tmUeg</a></p> <p>Senate Bill 214 text – <a href="https://www.legis.ga.gov/api/legislation/document/20252026/233014?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTAAAR21Ov5iwZLFeefwyNWpl7o8Qz_o4tICq-Z7uinQ_avlkocS4dYUcc3Kw6U_aem_V2FpMdWycNEFdSkRxUeJCQ">https://www.legis.ga.gov/api/legislation/document/20252026/233014?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTAAAR21Ov5iwZLFeefwyNWpl7o8Qz_o4tICq-Z7uinQ_avlkocS4dYUcc3Kw6U_aem_V2FpMdWycNEFdSkRxUeJCQ</a></p> <p>2018 National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine study on election security – <a href="https://nap.nationalacademies.org/read/25120/chapter/1">https://nap.nationalacademies.org/read/25120/chapter/1</a></p> <p>LinkedIn post from Dr. Wenke Lee on why he supports the use of hand-marked paper ballots – <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/why-computer-scientists-prefer-paper-ballots-wenke-lee/">https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/why-computer-scientists-prefer-paper-ballots-wenke-lee/</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Analysis,"/><category term="Legislation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Georgia Assembly is considering a bill to return the state to hand-marked paper ballots as the default, with touchscreen voting devices available for people with disabilities.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“What does ChatGPT Know about Information Systems?” accepted for publication at the Communications of the AIS</title><link href="https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2025/what-does-chatgpt-know-about-information-systems-accepted-for-publication-at-the-communications-of-the-ais/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“What does ChatGPT Know about Information Systems?” accepted for publication at the Communications of the AIS"/><published>2025-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2025/what-does-chatgpt-know-about-information-systems-accepted-for-publication-at-the-communications-of-the-ais</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2025/what-does-chatgpt-know-about-information-systems-accepted-for-publication-at-the-communications-of-the-ais/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently worked on a research project with <a href="https://www.marshall.usc.edu/personnel/daniel-edmund-oleary">Dan O’Leary</a>, <a href="https://robinson.gsu.edu/profile/veda-c-storey/">Veda Storey</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dr-french/">Aaron French</a>, <a href="https://robinson.gsu.edu/profile/joseph-buckman/">Joseph Buckman</a>, <a href="https://works.bepress.com/cecil-chua/about/">Cecil Chua</a>, <a href="https://www.graceyuangu.com/">Grace Gu</a>, <a href="https://www.slu.edu/business/about/faculty/niederman-fred.php">Fred Niederman</a>, <a href="https://www.marshall.usc.edu/personnel/francis-pereira">Francis Pereira</a>, <a href="https://business.wvu.edu/faculty-and-staff/directory/profile?pid=3499">Gary Templeton</a>, and <a href="https://acis.pamplin.vt.edu/directory/Wallace.html">Linda Wallace</a> that explored how well ChatGPT would do with exam and quiz questions used by faculty in Information Systems (IS) courses. I’m happy to report that our work has been accepted for publication in the Communications of the AIS.</p> <p>The study found that generative AI tools like ChatGPT performed well on actual exams and quizzes in general IS courses, database management, systems analysis and design, project management, and cybersecurity. ChatGPT earned a B average with multiple-choice and true/false questions and an A average on short answer/essay questions.</p> <p>We recommend that academia look at ways to implement AI tools in the classroom so that students can be prepared for their use in the workplace, rather than prohibiting their use. It’s our job to ensure that students are well prepared when they graduate, and AI is just the latest innovation we must incorporate into our teaching.</p> <p>The article is available for download at <a href="https://aisel.aisnet.org/cais/vol56/iss1/19/">https://aisel.aisnet.org/cais/vol56/iss1/19/</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academia,"/><category term="Research,"/><category term="Students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently worked on a research project with Dan O’Leary, Veda Storey, Aaron French, Joseph Buckman, Cecil Chua, Grace Gu, Fred Niederman, Francis Pereira, Gary Templeton, and Linda Wallace that explored how well ChatGPT would do with exam and quiz questions used by faculty in Information Systems (IS) courses. I’m happy to report that our work has been accepted for publication in the Communications of the AIS.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“To report or not to report? Extending Protection Motivation Theory to Vulnerability Discovery and Disclosure” accepted for publication at Computers &amp;amp; Security</title><link href="https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2024/to-report-or-not-to-report-extending-protection-motivation-theory-to-vulnerability-discovery-and-disclosure-accepted-for-publication-at-computers-&-security/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“To report or not to report? Extending Protection Motivation Theory to Vulnerability Discovery and Disclosure” accepted for publication at Computers &amp;amp; Security"/><published>2024-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2024/to-report-or-not-to-report-extending-protection-motivation-theory-to-vulnerability-discovery-and-disclosure-accepted-for-publication-at-computers-&amp;-security</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andygreenphd.github.io/blog/2024/to-report-or-not-to-report-extending-protection-motivation-theory-to-vulnerability-discovery-and-disclosure-accepted-for-publication-at-computers-&amp;-security/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been working with <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;user=ONmOYEMAAAAJ">Amy Woszczynski</a> and <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;user=MBkDFTMAAAAJ">DJ Oliver</a> on a study that is near and dear to my heart due to my personal experiences with reporting problems I have discovered. This week, we were informed that our study had been accepted for publication in “Computers &amp; Security,” an A-level journal on the Australian Business Deans Journal list. You can see the study at <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cose.2024.103880">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cose.2024.103880</a></p> <p>Vulnerability researchers are a class of people who look for weaknesses in software, hardware, or systems to alert organizations that may be vulnerable to the issues found. Unlike cybercriminals who seek to take advantage of these weaknesses, vulnerability researchers engage in these activities to be helpful.</p> <p>Currently, vulnerability researchers face an uphill struggle when trying to report problems they discover. For example, who does a vulnerability researcher contact at an organization when they find a problem? Reporting is also a risky proposition. There are numerous reported instances of organizations pursuing criminal charges or civil action against researchers, resulting in arrests, indictments, trials, and civil lawsuits.</p> <p>One possible solution to address this issue is for an organization to publish a vulnerability disclosure policy (VDP). A typical VDP will let researchers know what systems are in-scope for examination, who to report findings to, and explicitly state that researchers will not face repercussions from reporting if they follow the VDP. Unfortunately, many organizations either have badly constructed VDPs or don’t have one at all.</p> <p>Given the current climate, our research team wanted to examine the decision-making processes that vulnerability researchers undertake when faced with reporting in both VDP and non-VDP situations. To do this, we extended the Protection Motivation theory (PMT) in a novel context to help us study the problem. PMT has been used in prior security research to help understand how employees respond to fear-based appeals to engage in behaviors the organization wants them to, such as backing up data, having strong passwords, and so forth.</p> <p>In our context, vulnerability researchers do not work for the organization and would not be susceptible to the same types of fear appeals that organizations use on their employees. While employees are generally susceptible to fear-based appeals, we theorized that vulnerability researchers would not be. We created a survey instrument and sent it out to active vulnerability researchers to collect the data we needed to dig into the problem.</p> <p>Our analysis showed that organizations should reduce researchers’ fear perceptions and consider adaptive rewards for researchers in order to encourage reporting. We suggested that organizations could do these things by having a well-written VDP that clearly outlines system scope and reporting processes. Additionally, we suggested that organizations have a clearly written “safe harbor” section in the VDP that clearly outlines good faith reporting and provides assurances that organizations will not seek to have researchers arrested or sued civilly for reporting.</p> <p>This was a fun project, filled with challenges and frustrations along the way. We started work more than a year ago, and it’s nice to finally have it concluded and landed at a top-level journal. I’m especially grateful to have been a part of this team. Amy is a trusted mentor and longtime research partner, and I’m fortunate to be able to learn from her. I’ve known DJ since his time in our Ph.D. program at KSU, and he’s simply a good person and fun to work with and be around. I couldn’t ask for a better group to work with, and I’m lucky to be part of their team!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academia,"/><category term="Research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been working with Amy Woszczynski and DJ Oliver on a study that is near and dear to my heart due to my personal experiences with reporting problems I have discovered. This week, we were informed that our study had been accepted for publication in “Computers &amp; Security,” an A-level journal on the Australian Business Deans Journal list. You can see the study at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cose.2024.103880]]></summary></entry></feed>